Longbin **Lai**

■ (+86) 180 6795 0576 | **■** longbin.lai@gmail.com | **☆** lai.me | **□** longbinlai | **□** longbin-lai

Summary_

Dr. Longbin Lai is a distinguished expert in distributed systems and graph processing at Alibaba. He has played a crucial role in developing industry-standard and open-source systems such as GraphScope, GAIA, GLogS, and GOpt¹, which enhance interactive graph queries at Alibaba scale. These systems have contributed to GraphScope's record-breaking performance in the latest LDBC SNB benchmark² and are widely used in applications like money laundering detection and fraud analysis on Alibaba's platforms. Recently, at Alibaba Tongyi Lab, Dr. Lai is working on large-scale inference engines to improve the performance and reduce the cost of applying large language models.

Dr. Lai earned his Bachelor's and Master's degrees from Shanghai Jiao Tong University (SJTU) in 2010 and 2013, respectively. He completed his Ph.D. at the University of New South Wales (UNSW), Sydney, under the supervision of Prof. Xuemin Lin and Prof. Lu Qin in 2017 and continued his research there as a Postdoctoral Researcher. In 2019, he joined Alibaba Data Academy, where he focuses on developing distributed systems for Alibaba's e-commerce platforms.

Skills_

Programming Rust, Python, Java, C/C++, Cypher, Gremlin, SQL, Scala

Big Data Hadoop, Spark, Timely dataflow system, Flink, AWS Infrastructure

Big Graph GraphScope, Giraph/Pregel, GraphX, Gelly, Neo4J, GraphLab, TigerGraph

Machine Learning Tensorflow, PyTorch

Large Language Model DeepSpeed, vLLM, LangChain

Experience ____

Tongyi AI, Alibaba Group

Hangzhou, China

STAFF ENGINEER Oct. 2023 - Present

- Product development on LLM applications such as RAG and multi-agent engine,
- Work on the LLM inference systems, covering the topics of memory (KV-cache) management and application-driven scheduling strategies.

Alibaba Group Hangzhou, China

STAFF ENGINEER Dec. 2019 - Oct. 2023

- The architecturer and product manager of Graph Query Engine, a core component of Alibaba's graph platform: GraphScope (https://github.com/alibaba/graphscope).
- Work on large-scale and intelligent graph query processing system, especially distributed query execution, query compilation and optimization.

School of Computer Science and Engineering, UNSW

Sydney, Australia

RESEARCH ASSISTANT May. 2017 - May. 2019

- Design and implement big graph processing primitives and languages.
- Lead a team to develop graph pattern matching system.

Google Inc.Mountain View, CA, USA

TECH INTERN

Jan. 2017 - Apr. 2017

• Designed and implemented an emulator that simulates the Google backbone network and the routing strategies for testing, debugging and routing validation.

October 28, 2024 Longbin Lai · Résumé 1

¹Available at: https://github.com/alibaba/GraphScope/

 $^{^2} https://ldbcouncil.org/benchmarks/snb/LDBC_SNB_I_20240514_SF100-300-1000_graphscope.\\ pdf$

School of Computer Science and Engineering, UNSW

Sydney, Australia

PHD CANDIDATE, INDEPENDENT RESEARCH PROJECT

Jul. 2013 - May. 2017

- (**TwinTwigJoin**) Increased the performance of subgraph enumeration by up to an order of magnitude compared to the state-of-the-art by applying a decomposition-and-join framework in MapReduce.
- (SEED) Further improved the TwinTwigJoin by more than one order of magnitude by using a more advanced graph data storage mechanism (extending the traditional adjacency list) and an optimal join structure.

Department of Advertising and Searching, Alibaba Cloud Computing Corporation

HangZhou, China

RESEARCH INTERN, TEAM PROJECT

Jan. 2012 - Sep. 2012

- Designed and implemented a web recommendation system based on Alibaba cloud computing system (MapReduce-like system), which serves over 1000 top websites in China.
- Improved the throughput of the recommendation system to over 2 billion records per hour via a well-designed MapReduce data flow.
- Implemented a prototype of web classification algorithm that is twice faster than existing algorithm by solely using the url of the web page.

IBM Share-With-University Project

Shanghai, China

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, PROJECT LEADER

Oct. 2009 - Oct. 2010

- Saved the storage overhead of Hadoop File System (HDFS) by up to 30% without compromising the storage reliability by replacing the full replication mechanism with erasure coding.
- Improved the performance of Hadoop streaming utility (allowing coding with languages other than Java) by over 60% by replacing the synchronized inter-process communication module in Linux with desynchronized singleread-single-write queue.

Education

The University of New South Wales, Australia (UNSW)

Sydney, Australia

PHD. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jul. 2013 - Jul. 2017

• All courses Highly Distinguished

Shanghai Jiao Tong University (SJTU)

Shanghai, China

M.S. IN COMPUTER TECHNOLOGY

Sep. 2010 - Mar. 2013

• GPA 3.8 / 4.0, China's National scholarship, Top 2%

Shanghai Jiao Tong University (SJTU)

Shanghai, China

B.S. IN INFORMATION SECURITY

Sep. 2006 - Jun. 2010

• GPA 3.6 / 4.0, twice B-class SJTU academic scholarship, Top 15%

Honors & Awards

2021	C-class Talent , HangZhou 521 Project of Talent Introduction	Hangzhou, China
2012	Top 1% , China's National Scholarship	SJTU, China
2011	Top 4% , Tencent Academic Scholarship	SJTU, China
2010	Top 10% , Outstanding Graduate of Shanghai Jiao Tong University	SJTU, China
2009	Top 6% , Sony Academic Scholarship	SJTU, China
07, 08	Top 15% , B-Class SJTU Academic Scholarship	SJTU, China